Welcome back. I'm Jeffrey Brown of the PBS news hour and you are watching
PBS Books here at the Miami Book Fair in partnership with the Great American Read.
I'm joined now by Janet Fitch
But to talk about her new novel "The Revolution of Marina M."
Welcome to you.
Thank you.
The russian revolution. Huh?
What got you into that?
Well, I was history major. Russia was my field...
It was. Years goes back.
I took russian in highschool. I took russian in college.
I'm one of those people obsessed with russian literature
so it was sooner or later there would be a russian novel.
How much... so how much did you know of that period?
I had a pretty good grounding, but ...
when you're writing about people in history, it's different than writing history.
You have to have a pretty good grounding in what happen, but ...
it's more the texture of life you have to know
What do the phone... how do the phone work in 1916 ?
And how did the bread russian system work and what do the bread card look like?
So the devil's in the details.
So you had to know about these things and then decide how to use them in fiction.
Well, I tend to research and write in tandem.
Yeah
So I don't get too far down the rabbit hole ...
So... yeah! I... I found out what I need to know to work... to write that scene or that chapter.
So tell... so tell us about this book... well tho... this main character Marina.
Where did she come from?
(Who is she?)
Marina... is a ...
sixteen when the book opens during World War I, 1916
because Revolutions don't happen... you know by themselves. There's reasons.
It's World War I was a terrific disaster for Russia and for the... for tsar.
And she's a privileged girl. She's the daughter of intellectuals.
And she champions the revolution.
And when.. the Bolsheviks come into power in october...
her family comes apart — it's a liberal family not a radical family.
And she lives the life of the revolution.
She is a poet.
And I had begun the book as a novel inverse
You did?
Yeah!
For seventeen chapters ... in verse (reverse)
Wow!
And then...
Did you ever do that bevore?
No.
Because she's a poet, I thought her book should be a poetry, but...
the first I got to a place where I needed my fiction writer tools
to know what happen(ed) and then I was writing fictions.
So... so you hit on her as your main character and then... in research
I mean she based on any pret... any real person.
No. I had written a short story with the character in America as an émigré
And I never forgot about her.
And I returned to write... I wrote a short story about her.
And then I tried to write a nover about her in America.
And there were just too many things I didn't know about her.
So before I knew it, I was writing a story set during the Russian Revolution.
So well how far back where you're writing about her?
I mean, this... this initial short story.
It goes back to twenty...
(Is this year ago?)
This was between "White Oleander" and "Paint it Black"
I had a nover that failed.
But there was this character I love so after...
after "Paint it Black" came out I decided to write that short story.
And I just wanted... I wanted to be with her more.
That's inte... I maen people wonder where these... where these things come from. Right?
So this all... This is a big book, but it started with one character that.. from... that you thought of something else.
Right. Not even in this time and place.
yeah
You...
And she's very different...
You know it's again... It's a story about how young woman builds herself
through events and through reactions to things, decisions that she's made.
You know girl makes a decision in... at sixteen and she's... she has to live through it
and the woman becomes the result of that.
But unlike my two earlier books, I have character Sue (are) full of self-doubt.
mm-hmm
Whereas now I have a character who is absolutely confident.
And I've never had anybody like that.
I... I'm full of self-doubt.
I'm not used to be with somebody who knows what she thinks.
She can be totally wrong, things could go horribly astray as they do,
but it was f...
She's a more of a heroine type of character, that I've ever worked with before.
So what did that mean for the writing? Did she tell you what was gonna happen next?
They always do.
They do?
They always do. You just have to stay really close to the heartbeat of the character.
It's almost like leaning your head against her chest and hearing... hearing the heartbeat.
Of course in this case it's her story it's a young woman (coming away), but it's against some very big history
Right.
So it's the kind of things that happened to her are... it's not like what happened to most of... most young people.
Uh well, .. we all live in history.
You know very few people actually at the top making decisions.
Most of us are living where... we see the shadow on the wall, we care a rumor, we read the newpaper and
how people live in history realy interests me. And especially now.
Now it's...
When I was writing the book it was about the character — now it's me.
You know you get a strong sense of what that's like.
Yeah.
The blurb you're on the cover says: Marina is a female Zhivago.
So... I mean you can't read something like... book like this about the Russian Revolution without thinking of these models. Right?
Like a doctor Zhivogo.
Did  you know... did you have these models in mind?
Well. It's all goes into the pot. You know it's a big gumbo.
And it's russian literature
It's... I mean I encountered Zhivago far earlier than... than Pasternak's novel.
I encountered it on the sc... on the widescreen
Of course. Yeah.
In the little train going across the big snowy expanse
on the forty foot high faces Zhivago and Lara
I mean that brands you forever
Yeah.
What about russian literature, russian-write novelists?
Uh well I... I fell in love with russian literature.
I'm one of those people who is obsessed with russian literature.
And I encountered...
I encountered it for the first time as a junior high kid.
I was reading some... In English class that give you some treacly (trickly) female...
It was you know (crest) (cross) delehanty. People don't even read that anymore.
Cherry Ames, the student nurse, you know.
And it did not appeal to me at all.
I was infuriated. I came home and complained.
And my father gave me "Crime and Punishment".
So here. See you if you like that. And I... I loved it.
I loved it. It was so intense and extreme and...
people were you know they bludgeoned the landlady to death with an axe because of the philosophy.
It's like... Yeah! That is...
So I was... you know I was lost. I mean that was it for me
I took russian in... in high school. I took russian in college and...
it was only a matter of time before I tried a russian novel.
Do you think of this as a kinda departure for you from your other books
to going back in history and the epic nature of it?
Yeah. That... that was the departure
you know the building of woman, is similar.
But the actual amount of time and energy to construct a world
was something very new. I'm a writer of place. And time is also...
What does that mean? you...
You know place is very important. I need to know where things happen. There's a map in the book.
My imagi... That's how my imagination works. It's very geographical.
And... but time is also a place. The past is a country as well.
So it's constructing the world that I have to...
you know I have to... I... I'm from LA. I was able to do it with first two novels (to do the first)
with a foundation anyway of place.
But Petersburg... I was a student there in 1977
so I knew it somewhat, but I had to learn it the way someone who lived there, who grew up there and knew it.
And you did that through books...
I did it through reading. I went to Russia couple times. I'd also been a student there so you know for the memory
I'd also been a student there so you know for the memory...
I read a lot of women's memoirs so things that weren't intended for publication,
but just women talk thinking about their lives. Very valuable.
You haven't you are telling me before we started... I was commenting on that cover
And you were said that you got... you got involved in the details of the cover.
Yes. And this is something so rare. Publisheres usually don't let the writer interfere,
because we're generally not visual people. We're people of the word.
But I needed it to be historical accurate.
The hair was not quite 1916-1917
at one point she bobs her hair which people did.
But before that the hair was very full and low
The hair had to change, I cut her nai... I asked them to cut her nails,
because they didn't have manicures during the Revolution.
So yeah, little details. But the overall design was theirs.
So... so... I'm curious when you... because it's... it's story of one young woman but in the history
It... you there has to be a balance. Right? I mean you have to let us as readers know what's going on in the history.
Yes.
So how's... where's the balance for you?
Is that something you wondered about as you were writing or you read about?
Well the balance for me is I know so much more about that history, than I want to subject the reader to.
Because I... I was... history was my field.
So the politics of the Revolution is very intricate
and an american without background you can only expect people to digest a certain amount
And you really only technically need what people require to understand the scene,
to understand what's going on, what's in the air.
I had people read it who have trouble following politics — they don't follow history very well.
And I... I thought you know to construct solidly enough that
someone who is not history buff can follow it easily. That's what I wanted.